Guide to the Isaacs/Hofeller Family Papers, 1919-2002 MS 903
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Isaacs/Hofeller Family Papers
1919-2002
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kuper, Elaine Hofeller
MS 903
.50 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of one box containing correspondence; books; event materials, including dance programs and wedding invitations; bulletins; newsletters and news clippings; a photograph; and a VHS cassette featuring an interview with 104 year old Lorraine Isaacs Hofeller regarding the 1900 Galveston storm. Materials in the collection range from 1919 to 2002.
Biographical / Historical
Lorraine Isaacs was born February 24, 1896 in Galveston, Texas. She was elected president of her graduating class (1913) at Galveston's Ball High School – the first girl to hold the office, defeating four male opponents. Lorraine was four years old when the Galveston storm devastated the island on September 8, 1900. Lorraine's parents and brother survived the storm, as did their house, although it sustained moderate damage.
Sigmar K. Hofeller was born in New York, November 12, 1895. He moved to Texas from Buffalo, New York, during World War I as a member of the U.S. Army Signal Corps. Lorraine and Sigmar met in Fort Worth while he was station there. The couple married in Galveston in 1919. They moved to Houston in 1934, where Lorraine sold insurance. The couple had two children: Elaine and Marion. The family were members of Congregation Beth Israel in Houston.
Sigmar Hofeller died on May 3, 1964. Lorraine died July 17, 2002 at the age of 106 and was the last survivor of the 1900 storm. The two are interred at the Hebrew Benevolent Society Cemetery in Galveston.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence; books; event materials, including dance programs and wedding invitations; bulletins; newsletters and news clippings; a photograph; and a VHS cassette document the lives of the Isaacs and Hofeller families and their activities within the Galveston and Houston Jewish communities between 1919 and 2002. Of particular interest is a documentary on the 1900 Galveston storm, which features an interview with 104 year old Lorraine Isaacs Hofeller.
Conditions Governing Access
The material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Elaine Hofeller Kuper in September 2019.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged chronologically in one series as follows:
Series I: General
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
programs (documents); videotapes; clippings (information artifacts); photographs
Places
Texas--Galveston
Subjects (Persons)
Kuper, Elaine Hofeller
- Series I: General
  - Lorraine and Sigmar's wedding invitation, 1919-01-09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Rabbi Henry Cohen and a wedding invitations (photocopies from items scanned), 1919-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book- "The Ceremonies of Judaism" from Beth Israel Library, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book- "The Oppenheim Pictures," inscribed to Elaine Hofeller for Chanakuh, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Golden Jubilee program commemorating Dr. Henry Cohen's 15th anniversary, 1938-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sigma Alpha Rho dance programs, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ramblers Club Basketball Tournament/Banquet Charity Dance programs, 1940-01-14; 1941-02-16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Delta Epsilon Beta dance program, 1940-01-28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - B.Z.B. Pot-o-Gold Dance program, 1940-03-24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AZA Second Birthday Party program, Chapter 136, 1940-04-21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MM Society 17th Annual Charity Dance program, 1940-12-22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Houston Zionists Purim Ball and Queen Esther Contest programs, 1940; 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Houston Community Players "Howdy Stranger" program, 1941-05-19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Congregation Beth Israel weekly bulletins, 1946-10-1974-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beth Israel News, monthly newsletter, 1952; 1954; 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Congregation Beth Israel confirmation programs, 1959-06-12; 1966-05-27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Congregation Beth Israel teachers, group photograph, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - News clippings, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Galveston storm documentary [VHS], featuring an interview with Lorraine Isaacs Hofeller, 2000 (Box 1)